A resurrendered life, a resurrected life.
Lord, I pray in Jesus' name that you would bring a special blessing to Karina and her family as they continue to walk this journey.
Father, I pray that you would bless our hearts and our minds and our thoughts and our resurrender on a daily basis
that we might receive from your Spirit the manna for today.
To live and walk and journey in the name of Jesus.
That you'd name that we pray.
And all the saints pray.
Amen.
You may be seated.
You may stand up.
It's on a new way out of it.
I like it.
It was, so I didn't know that song.
And you know when you, like, first learn a song and you think you got it and you try to close your eyes and try to look and close your eyes and worry, you know.
And when my kids were little, they used to make up words all the time.
Like my one daughter created the word organizing, organizing design.
And I started singing and I thought it said, instead of resurrender, I thought it said resurrection.
And halfway through the word, I realized I wasn't singing what everyone else was singing.
But from that point on, I thought, you know, resurrection.
It's kind of a, there is a fresh resurrection in our own lives.
And we resurrender again, day in and day in.
So we've been walking through a series on critical pieces for those who want to be a partner, partner with this church, a member of this church, a covenant person.
As we joined together as a congregation, two weeks ago, we talked about the word.
We really do value the word.
We rely on the word.
It's a standard for faith and practice.
It's also a primary means by which we commune and connect with God.
He speaks to us.
He evaluates and analyzes us through his word.
And we get to understand him through his word.
Last week, we talked about salvation.
Salvation big ass, not just moment in time way back when, but the journey of salvation that we all walked,
the past and present and future sense of salvation, and try to talk about all that means.
Today, we're going to talk about the church.
I made a comment a few weeks ago, and I saw the comments that most would know,
and a few people come up and say, hey, how do you know that?
But the word church, a place here in the New Testament,
pretty much always, but maybe two places, and those two places are questionable.
Almost always, it refers to a local body of Jesus followers.
A concrete, concretized group that you can identify.
And then, so today, I want to unpack some of what that means.
Again, the last two, I did a flyover of the word, a flyover of the salvation.
Today, instead of a flyover, I'm going to try to dig down into two illustrations of church
that I think will be helpful for us, at least I hope they'll be helpful for us,
as we move forward as a body of Jesus followers.
So, the focus today is the local church, and if I can, like I did the last few weeks,
I just want to walk through the little piece of membership covenant that we'll be using.
I promise to accept biblical instruction, this is the third paragraph in what we're going to do in a bit,
I think in a month.
And when we say, I promise to accept biblical instruction, it doesn't mean I promise to accept and believe what I've been taught.
Ryan, several weeks ago, talked about the difference between the Thessalonians and the Bereans,
when the gospel was preached, and the Thessalonians, they resorted to what they always knew to be true,
and they lost that.
And the Bereans relied on what God had given them in the past,
but they also urged the Scriptures to see if this is true.
And that's really the attitude, the mindset, when we say,
that I promise to accept biblical instruction, it's that of the Bereans.
So, I have a really good friend of medical doctors, he trains medical doctors,
he writes a newsletter for medical doctors,
I subscribe to his newsletter, and so I get it every, I don't know,
if every other week, every week, I'm not sure if it's periodically.
And he tends to take two or three medical issues,
and go through the research,
and then help unpack those aspects of the medical research,
and about every third one is something that I understand,
and I actually care about,
because it has something to do with my own personal health,
and my wife, and my kids,
and so I just keep up the gate.
Plus, I really believe in investing in various areas of knowledge and understanding,
because it makes a more well-rounded person.
Anyways, in this last newsletter,
he had a psychiatrist who was also a medical doctor,
who was talking about his days in medical school,
and what he learned,
and he said,
if we always used to say back to medical school,
that 50% of what we teach you will be wrong.
We just don't know which 50%.
I hope the staffs aren't that guy for theological training,
but I can almost guarantee you that much of what,
some of what you've been taught in the past,
and perhaps some of what you're being taught now,
is wrong.
We don't know what part that is,
and that's why we approach as the brains.
The Scripture is our standards.
We go back to the Scriptures.
Having said that,
would anyone here want a medical doctor
that never went to med school?
We, of course, must.
We recognize that we need trained,
and we need taught,
and we need trained and taught
with a humble attitude toward the data.
And in this context,
our data is the word of God.
And so,
that's what we mean by,
oh, you do know the word disciple?
I realize you've kind of given it,
like,
churchy jargon.
It means something in the church world.
But the word disciple literally means learning.
A disciple,
if so fast though,
by definition of the word,
is a learning.
And so,
if you're not a learner,
you're not a disciple.
Part of discipleship is learning,
so that's why we agree
to accept biblical instruction.
Okay,
I'll try to go through a little faster.
I promise to accept biblical instruction
and to contribute
to a loving and united church family.
And that's going to be the crux
of what I want to talk about today.
But I'll go through the rest of this
to explain that key statement,
that that's what we do.
I promise to accept biblical instruction
and to contribute
to a loving and united church family
through my regular attendance.
I like that it says
contribuously
because much of American Christianity
is about what I get by attendance.
A really good friend of mine
at a Christmas service,
Christmas Eve service,
one time said,
why is it always
that after Christmas
we go back to school,
we go back to our job,
we go back to our friend group,
we go back to other family
that we didn't see.
And the first question
that everyone asks is,
what did you get for Christmas?
He said,
it's welcome,
you know what I have.
What did you get for Christmas?
With the same information you want.
He said,
I hope that we can be,
and he said that,
and I think it's too fresh too,
I hope that we can say,
not just,
what did you get
from a loving church today?
What are you going to ask the question,
what did you give?
What did you contribute?
How were you part of the body of Christ
that were iron sharpens iron,
where we take the multitude of gifts
that we've had
and serve one another?
And when I say church,
I'm not talking about
the Sunday morning hour and a half
when we all gather together.
This is the gathering of the church.
But you are the church,
and the ministers of the church
are really outside of this
hour and a half of it.
Hopefully there's all kinds of ministries,
and so the question becomes,
how do we contribute,
and in this case,
to our regular attendance,
and you can unpack it
a little bit more,
with time,
finances,
spiritual gifts
that God has given you.
So I like to say this,
people call me what they value.
I would say to them,
you know what,
sell me your date book
and your checkbook,
and I'll tell you
what you're really about.
Because where we invest
our time,
where we invest
our money,
our capabilities,
our capacities,
our abilities,
our spiritual gifts,
by the way,
all of which are given
by God,
says more about
what we value
than what we claim
that we value.
By the way,
if any of you happen
to be spiritually gifted
in the help of service,
you know that it's help
and service,
it's something you do
and you like to do,
a real practical application
of this message
will be show up tonight
at 5.15,
and help me take down
all these chairs
and set up tables
for the 80 or so people
who will be coming
tonight.
It's a shameless plug.
Because otherwise,
I'm going to do it all myself
and I don't want to do it.
But I won't
because I know
what kind of church you want.
Okay.
I promise to accept
biblical instruction
and contribute
to a loving
and healthy family
through my regular attendance
with my time,
finance,
spiritual gifts
that God has given me.
I submit
to supporting
the ministries
of this church.
By the way,
that's what we're doing tonight.
Tonight,
the goal is to help people
either discover
or reaffirm
or maybe
do a little correction
on how God
has gifted you
and wired you.
My wife,
in our training today,
she told a wonderful story
of working with someone
about their spiritual gifts
who had been doing it
for 35 years
and they knew
what their gifts were
and as they were getting older,
they could no longer
do those things
the way they used to
and they were lamenting it
and they were sad about it.
And she said,
well,
let's take a look
at these secondary gifts
and she listed out
the secondary gifts
and that began
a decking
of reorienting
how he served
the kingdom of God
in these secondary gifts
that he had
to keep the glory
and the capacity
and the strength
of the wisdom
after there's so many years
of serving to do it.
So,
it can be that as well
so if you want to discover
and if you're one of these people
who says,
I know all my gifts,
I don't need to come.
No, no, no,
you need to come
because you need to help
the other people
figure it out.
That's part of what we do.
That's the way it works.
Okay.
So, that's the covenant.
What I'd like to do
with that then
is really focus
on this statement.
Conceiving to a loving
and united
so strongly.
I want to do it through
two extreme examples.
One biblical
where it went really bad
and one historical
where it went really good.
but before I do that
I want to re-name
this membership stuff
and I'm not rebranding
that'll be later
we're still calling it
membership
but I had a really
interesting conversation
actually with Ryan
and Jamie
talking about language.
What's the language
that we use?
Is membership
a good language?
What does that communicate?
Because for some people
that communicates
the radio station
W-I-I-S-M
you know that station?
What's in it for me?
What do I get out of it?
And we love to tune into that
and say
someone floated the idea
of partnership.
Does partnership
communicate something?
But it was not
that's a good word
but that comes
with some baggage too
from ways we might
not want to look at it.
I use for covenant.
Do we join?
Do we partner?
Do we covenant?
What does it mean?
And you do know
that writing is not
I mean one was
really nice.
I had a good friend
who was planting
a biker church
in Nebraska.
He took over
an old biker bar
and was doing
an amazing job
planting the church
and he realized
that he had
a lot of new believers
a lot of converse
who loved Jesus
who were excited
for Jesus
but their
biblical knowledge
was really lasting.
And so he decided
we need to teach
these people
more than what I can
give in a sermon.
And so he decided
to start a Sunday
school program
and he launched it
and he worked
feverishly to
establish this
Sunday school program
for a couple months
and like
two people showed up.
He kept pitching it
and pitching it
and nobody was showing up.
So the next week
he stood up
and he said
look I love you guys
you know I made a mistake
I launched a Sunday
school program
it hasn't worked
we're not doing it.
Done.
And that's when he got up
and he said
so I've really been praying
and we're launching
a new program
on Sunday morning
before church
because it's hard
to get people
other nights
we're going to start
a new program
for road warriors
and he passed
the place out.
Same thing.
Christian education.
It's giving people
the word
in the way
that life
can't form it today.
And so
I've been kind of
toying with this
whole word
and in that meeting
I ask
well what if
we just
took the biblical
injunction
and turned it
into a verb
because you know
the Bible
says a whole lot
about what we should
do with one another.
And so what if
we just
threw in the verb
that we are going
to carry these
intentionally
to one another
as the Bible
says it.
I know you're
looking at me like
what are you
talking about me?
Let me just
let me read a couple
really quick.
Be at peace
with one another.
Watch one another's feet.
Love one another.
That one comes up
over and over
and over again.
Be devoted
to one another
in brotherly love.
Honor one another
above yourselves.
Learn in harmony
with one another.
Instruct one another.
Greet one another.
And this one says
with a holy kiss
I think we can
contextualize that
as a warm and
ready for handshake.
But greet one another.
Love one another.
By the way,
you do know
it's really hard
to do any of these
while you're all
looking up at me
in the back
of each other's heads.
Is that fair?
It's really hard.
This is important.
It's a critical piece
of our collective life.
And we're thrilled
that if people come
to hear the word
and to worship
together
and to receive
communion
and experience
public baptism
and all of those
things,
that's awesome.
That somehow
these one another
is that the Bible
is very clear
that we're to do.
If we're going
to be the church,
at least the biblical
concept of the church,
a local body
that acts like
the called
Alphardus
the Ecclesia,
then we definitely
need to find ways
to do these things.
Galatians 6, verse 2,
Caring each other's
burdens.
Be patient.
Bearing with one
another in love.
There's that word again.
Forgiving each other.
And by the way,
today I hope
with the positives
and the negative examples,
the biblical
and the historical,
that we'll see
where this didn't go well
and the outcome
and where this went
unbelievably well
and the outcome.
Before forgiving
one another.
Submitting to one another.
That is reverence
for Christ.
Wow, there's a big one.
Submission is not
a world that
we in America
like very much.
The Bible loves it.
There's a sense
of submitting
to one another.
Deferring
In humility,
consider others
better than yourself.
Bear with each other.
Monish one another.
Make your love
increase and overflow.
Encourage one another.
Build each other.
Are you getting
the concept?
I'm only thinking
about every story
that's on my list
and I still have
about 20,
30 more to get.
And by the way,
the end of the list
is again,
eight times,
love one another,
love one another.
You've heard the story
about the Apostle John
who was a big one
and love one another.
At the end of his life,
old man is one of the,
it's one of the only
apostles we think
that actually got
to live to an old life.
The rest of them
all died
tomorrow's death.
And at the end
of his life,
they asked him,
you know,
all of these years
that you have served
the Lord Jesus,
all of these years
that you have walked
and you have ministered
to the church
that we know
is coming to an end.
Teach us something
that we need to know.
Give us,
give us what's
a French one.
And you looked at it
and you said,
love one another.
Love one another.
It's what becomes
a French one.
Okay,
I don't think
I need to listen
anymore of those.
I think you get it.
If not,
human-ass words
and I'll beat you
so much.
Okay,
so let me give you
two quick examples.
The first is from
2 Samuel
and it's the story
of Ahithophel.
There we go.
2 Samuel 16.23.
Now,
in those days,
the advice of Ahithophel,
was like that of one
who requires of God.
That was how both
David and Absalom,
Absalom's son,
David's son,
regarded all of
Ahithophel's advice.
Ahithophel was considered
a godly man
who the king looked to
for advice
and it was a story
that went incredibly fast
in the worst possible way.
Those of you who know
your Bible well,
you know that King David
was a man after God's own heart.
He loved God.
He wrote a lot of the Psalms.
He loved the kings.
He was a great king.
And he also was the father
of an incredibly
dysfunctional family.
Or an incredibly
And we're going to share
some of the dysfunction
that went on in his family.
But my first takeaway
on this, by the way,
is that you can be
an incredibly godly person
and still have
an incredibly
dysfunctional family.
And I hate to say this,
but if you have
an incredibly
dysfunctional family,
you're probably
a contributor to that
in some way.
And you can still be
an incredibly godly person.
There is this,
I don't get it,
but it's true.
My favorite,
like a little meme
or one little cartoon,
is this huge auditorium.
And in this huge auditorium,
there's three people
in the whole auditorium.
And on the back of it
is this big band
and it's an annual gathering
of adult children
of non-dysfunctional families.
So a few of us
have a vacant.
Well,
so how dysfunctional
was his family.
Absalom,
this guy,
he had a sister
named Tomah
and one of David's
other sons,
Absalom's
half-brother,
raped
Absalom's
sister Tomah.
Absalom
did not handle it well.
And non-definitely,
he was a perpetrator.
But David
did not handle it well.
As if the fellow
you'll see
did not handle it well.
The only person
in the Scriptures
that I think
handled it well
was the victim,
Tomah.
She was,
she's part of the only
hero of the story.
The rest
in the midst of their
dysfunction,
things just
got
worse.
So we're going to
hear the story of
how David's son,
Absalom,
decided that
David was no longer
going to be king
and that he was
going to take over.
And then David's
old age,
probably in 60s,
Absalom had
garnered enough
support and came in
and David had to
flee Jerusalem
with a group
of loyal followers.
And just like in the
beginning of his
ministry when he was
anointed king,
but he was still
hiding out in
the desert hiding
in a cave from
his father-in-law.
Now he's out in
that same desert
hiding in some
of the same caves
from the sun
who's taking over
his nation.
I can't imagine
when a crew
is enacted
by your own
town.
I can't imagine
the motions of it.
Interesting to me,
by the way,
if you ever want to
do a fascinating
study,
many of our
psalms,
there's like a
little line
before the psalm
that tells you
the historical
context of the
psalm.
And FYI,
those little
context things,
we believe they
were actually
part of the
original.
So many of
those contexts,
unlike the rest
of your Bible
which has like
little context,
like little
headlines and
headers telling
you the situation,
those are actually
in the Scriptures.
And so there's
the part of
the inspired
word of God.
And so we can
rest assured
on some of,
and not all
of them have
context,
but some of
them have
very clear
context about
who's saying
it and what's
the context
in which
he's saying
it.
And it's a
fascinating
study to
read David's
psalms that
he wrote when
he was being
chased by his
father-in-law
at the beginning
of his ministry,
which is that.
But then also
those ones that
he wrote at
the end of
his life when
he's being
chased by
his son.
He's being
king, and
he's being
removed, and
he writes
these psalms.
And what's
fascinating, you
do the study,
read it, this
is like extra
credit for all
of you.
These over
here, David
is like,
oh!
And over
here, he's
like, God, I
have a problem,
and I know
you're good.
This is
incredible,
emotional stability
having walked
with God for
so many
years, and
ups and
downs, and
all of
his
function of
family, all
of his
function of
life, and
staying faithful
to God in
the midst of
it, repenting
when he's
caught, not
just excusing
his stuff, but
repenting,
hearing it
publicly, that
David to a
place where
even in a
worse
situation, he
could have a
fine confidence
that God
still didn't
control us.
And he
still did it.
This
psalm, we
don't know the
exact context
of this one,
it doesn't
have that
little, you
know, Psalm
55-0, it
doesn't have
that voice, but
we know it's a
psalm on
David's
betrayed, and
many commentators
think that this
phrase is actually
David talking
about
Epiphany, this
prophet of
God, this
kingly
counsel, who
David relied
on, and as
you see in the
story, it's
going to betray
David, it's
going to turn
on David.
David writes
that it is
you, a man
like myself, my
companion, my
close friend, with
whom I once
enjoyed sweet
fellowship at the
house of God as
we walked among
the worshipers, and
then the rest is
about who I
do, and I
said it.
Listen,
Phil didn't
handle it
super way.
Okay, next
voice.
So, we're
going to continue
the story.
Philip was
offering
sacrifice, so
the context
of the story,
Philip is
marched into
Jerusalem, he's
taken over the
kingship, David
has run, David
is gone, now
he's having
sacrifices offered
to anoint him
as a new king,
letting all of
Israel know that
I'm now in
charge, David's
no longer in
charge, and
while Philip
was offering the
sacrifice, he
also begs for
a hippopotam.
He begs for this
counselor of
king David, to
come from his
hometown, and
so the
conspiracy gained
strength, and
absolutes kept
following, kept
on increasing.
A hippopotam was
summoned, a
hippopotam came,
and a hippopotam
joined the
two.
Okay?
Okay, next
thing.
So, a hippopotam
is now giving
absolute
counsel.
What should I
do?
I've taken over
the kingship,
we didn't get
the king, the
king ran, he
hiding with some
of his mighty
men, and he
still, he still
are, he still
has some
followers, but
I'm now in
charge, what
should I do?
And a hippopotam
says, well, here's
what I want you
to do, Aslan.
I want you to
take a tent and
put it up on the
top of the
palace, so all
Israel can see
the tent, and
one by one by
one, all of
David's
concubines, I
want you to
parade them up
to the tent, go
into the tent
with them, and
let all Israel
know that you're
sleeping with
David's
concubines.
Now, there's a
different era, we
don't have
concubines today,
so let us
understand that
please.
I don't know
how long they
took, but
David know a
lot of them.
We're talking
day upon day
upon night
shaming,
who are
succinct
in front of
all of
Israel.
Now, I
don't think
they saw
what was in the
tent, but
it's not
hard to
drop.
It was
intentional,
destructive.
That's a
fitness
cell's
first piece
of advice,
destructive
piece of
advice.
And this
is also
excellent.
I will
choose 12,000
men and
set out
tonight in
pursuit of
David.
I would
accept him
while he
was weary
and weak.
I would
strike him
with terror.
And then
all the
people with
him were
free,
and I'll
strike him
down for
you.
And this
is our
first
recommendation
is
saying
David
by sleeping
with all
of his
concubines
so all
of the
followers
of King
David
can see
what is
going on.
And second,
let me
take a
whole bunch
of people
and go
out and
slap them
down and
let me
kill them.
That's one
of David's
spiritual
advisors.
How do you
have done
so far
in the
South
place
that?
How do you
help me?
understand it?
How do you
I want to
see if I
can give you
a little
insight into
how that
happened
because it's
an extended
dysfunctional
family reality
going on
here.
Except in
Samuel 11,
3,
he tells us
that Bathsheba,
and you
remember the
story of
Bathsheba?
She was a
young woman
who was
outside
bathing at a
time when
women bathed
outside and
men didn't
go up on
roofs.
I was
just up
at my
mom's
house for
the 4th
of July,
and my
daughter and
husband came
in, and
my brother and
his wife and
a 16-year-old
daughter came
in, and my
other daughter
came in, and
my mom has
this beautiful
house, and
many of us
would like
downstairs, but
upstairs is just a
huge room, multiple
beds, and we
just go swept up
there as a group.
But when you're all
asleep, when your
kids are this big,
it's really easy.
But when your
kids are adults,
they're dynamic
to change a
little bit.
And so before
you come up
the stairs, I'm
coming up, honey,
and is it okay?
When you get up, I
would get up at
like 5 in the
morning, and I'd
want to go
downstairs and do
stuff, and you're
over there
sleeping, and I'd
just kind of like
duck down behind
the bed, and
change out of my
pajamas, and put
them up.
It's just
irrespectful.
If someone is
putting it in the
bathroom, you
kind of turn
around and get
yourself busy
with something
else.
Oh, that's the
way it was
when the women
gave, and the
Scripture tells
us that in the
time when kings
go to war, David
was at home.
The state
one.
two, he went
up on top of
the roof.
I'm on board.
I'm going to go
up on the roof.
That's kind of
the dark internet
of the day, I
guess.
He sees
Bathsheba.
He calls for
He sleeps with
Bathsheba.
And Bathsheba
gets pregnant.
And quite
frankly, with the
power differential
between the
king and
Michelle woman,
I don't think
it was too
financial.
I don't know.
But it was a
gross violation.
And then, when
she gets pregnant,
he stands for
her husband, who
is actually out
at war, where
David was
supposed to be,
to come on
back.
His plan was
Uriah would come
back, sleep
with his wife,
and no one
would know the
difference.
And when
Uriah came
back, Uriah
said, no, I
can't do that.
I mean, if my
men are out
there fighting
and suffering,
I can't go and
enjoy all of
these meals and
all this time
with my life.
He said, guards
in the garden.
And after the
second, David
actually got him
in and got him
drunk, hoping
that might work.
And after the
second or third
night, he's like,
okay, that's not
going to work.
And so he
said, Uriah
back to the
front with a
letter saying,
please give this
letter to the
general.
When the
general got the
letter, he read
it, and what
it said was,
when you're in
the heat of a
battle, put
Uriah in the
very front.
When Uriah is
engaged in battle
in the front,
grab the rest of
your people and
pull them back.
It was a plan of
murder.
This is David's
worst point.
Believe it.
So here we
have in 2
Samuel 11, 3,
Bathsheba is the
daughter of Eliam.
And in 2
Samuel 23, 34,
Eliam is the
son of Ahithophon.
In other words,
Bathsheba was
his game
daughter.
Now, we
don't know the
exact time
study, but
people much
wiser than
me who study
much more than
I do.
In his old
question and
survey, James
Smith says that
probably David
was 58 when
he violated
Bathsheba.
And when
Ahithophel
advised
Absalom,
David's son,
to do these
things,
David was
probably 64.
So six years
after violating
Bathsheba,
Ahithophel
soothing the
opportunity,
goes and
joins the
crew,
and his
two pieces
of advice
are due
to David
what David
did to my
granddaughter and
grandson.
sexually
violate and
murder.
Take a
piece of
thought from
a family.
Folks,
you can get
a way out of it.
Calvary 4,
verse 23,
says,
Above all
us,
go to
heart.
Because
everything else
flows from it.
I used to do a
lot of
wound work with,
psychological,
spiritual wound work
with pastors.
And we used to
try to get them
to get to their
place of wounding
and meet Jesus
in that place of
wounding.
because a wound
that is not
transformed gets
to the spread.
That when we
don't deal with
our stuff,
our stuff just
kind of eeps
out into
everyone else.
It's the
angry man
that yells at
someone else,
you're just so
angry!
And all they're
doing is
suggesting.
They're suggesting
their own
issues out there
that they can't
deal with
anything here.
Folks,
the fault
point is
contingent.
And you're
not immune.
And the
vaccine
for wounding
and the
contingent
of wounding
is to
one another.
It's to
intentionally
in the
presence of
God
say,
I will
forgive you.
bear your
burden.
I will
choose to
love you.
Now,
I realize
it's not a
terminal
challenge.
It's not a
terminal
challenge.
But only
by allowing
ourselves to
stand before
God and
realize,
first of all,
how far we
have violated
God.
How we
need real
forgiveness.
And we
ever get to
a place to
be able to
say,
I don't
forget it,
I forgive it.
I'm not
going to let you
violate me
again that way.
I'm just
getting buried
down this.
But I
already need to
forgive you.
Because this
is a story
of
dysfunctional
family going
really,
really
into it.
The truth is
folks, most
of us are
wounded in
community.
And God
has so
designed it
with our
feelings
that
generally
comes in
the
community.
It's when
we find
new episodic
encounters
with God
and with
brothers and
sisters and
community that
can begin to
get at that
stuff that
drives us,
that God
sees why,
the Scriptures
of pull of
we do one
another.
One another is
not just about
what he did
for you,
but it's about
in that
actually what
God does
in me.
Look how
God begins
to change
me.
I can't
tell you how
many people
I've played
with change
in the midst
of praying
honestly if
they were
changed,
God changed
me.
You know,
it's the
old
Mason to
David,
he tells
him a
story,
David to
Paul,
a second,
and Mason
says,
you're that
man.
And then
David writes
Psalm 51,
against you and
you only have
I sinned and
none of you
don't in sight.
Do not
take me from
your presence.
do not take
me from your presence.
It's incredible
for patience.
So the story
only gets worse.
It's the last
piece of the
story I tell you.
So there's
a second
counselor,
spiritual
advisor,
and he
states
faithful to
David.
And so he
goes in
and he
asks him
pretends
that he's
committed
and he
gives
advice
and his
is
intentional
to keep
David from
following all
of Ahithophel's
advice.
He couldn't
do anything
about the
tent up
on the
top,
but he
did get
Ahithophel's
keys not to
go to David
and not let
Ahithophel go
and kill David
and give David
time to be able
to recover
and eventually
take back
the kingdom.
And when Ahithophel
saw that his
advice had not
been followed,
he sat at
his donkey
and set
out for
his house
and his
home
he put
his house
in order
and then
he handed
himself.
Thank you.
Thank you for
negative.
Let's go on
to a more
sort of positive
reason I'm
going to use
a historical
picture,
a story of a
group of men
women who
double down
and chose
one another.
They chose
community,
unity,
above almost
everything else.
Now, in full
disclosure,
while I have
known about
the Moradians
and I have
known some
of the stuff
of the Moradians,
this week
I have the
privilege of
proofing our
own
Kent McKay's
master's thesis
on the Moradians.
And as I'm
proofing it,
you know,
I think I'm
doing him a
service and
the whole time
I'm teaching
I'm going,
this is really
good.
Oh, this is
good for
the, you know,
I've got to
say, Kent,
thank you for
the material.
And if any
of it is
wrong, it's
Kent's fault.
Okay.
So, let me
start by saying,
oh, and the
other thing is
that there's
so much to
say about
the Moradians,
but God
has begun a
journey with
them 300
years before
the time that
I'm going to
talk about.
And there
were so
many ups
and downs
and lanes
and just
everything that
God was
forming them
and moving
them until
they got to
this place
between 1720
and 1730s,
in those two
decades, where
everything seemed
to gel.
And God
used literally
a few hundred
immigrant poor
believers to
radically change
the world.
I mean,
radically change
the world.
It
vomited on
what they
called the
Moradian
Pentecost
on August
13th of
1727, the
end of
three days of
spontaneous
grassroots
revival, where
people were
testifying the
Spirit came so
powerfully that
they didn't
know whether
they were in
heaven or
on earth.
They couldn't
tell.
And the
Spirit of God
came, and
from that
point, within
12 days, they
began an
uninterrupted
24-hour
prayer cycle,
where several
believers would
sign up for
each hour of
the day.
And for 24
hours, they
would pray.
Each one would
pray for an
hour with a
couple other
people.
Now, if we
instituted
that, I
would be
proud of us
if we got a
full 24-hour
because the
2 o'clock in
the morning slot
is really hard
to tell people
out.
If we could
do that for
a week, I
feel pretty
good.
I mean, if
we could
actually, three
or four of
us are always
present, and
every hour of
the day for
24 hours, and
we do it for
a week, and
we'd be like,
that'd be
awesome, what
would God do
with that?
Imagine if we
did it for a
year.
And if you
imagine what
that would
do, it would
allow hearts
into the
kingdom, and
the Moranians
did it for
a hundred
years, 12
days after
their own
10-month
movement.
They started
a prayer, 24-hour
prayer cycle,
lasted a
many years.
Within 12
months, they
sent out their
first missionaries
to Greenland
and to the
West Indies.
They were so
committed to
the mission
work that they
were doing,
that those who
went to the
West Indies,
they said,
we want to
reach your
best ways.
They didn't
have any
great training
except what God
had done to
them in their
life.
They didn't
go to
missionary
training school.
They didn't
do a
development
program.
They didn't
read the
biographies.
In fact,
at that point,
very few
Western Christians
were doing
missions at
all.
This is
free William
Carey.
They're just
not doing it.
And so
they feel
committed,
they go,
and they
send them to
West Indies,
and they
say,
we're going
to go and
work among
the poor
slaves,
and we're
going to do
no matter
what.
And they
say,
even if we
have to
sell ourselves
into slavery,
God's calling
us to do
this.
We'll do
that to
communicate with
the slaves
and we
send for
Jesus.
I mean,
is that a
pretty big
commitment?
And some of
you are
thinking,
boy,
that almost
sounds
culture now.
You do
know that
Eris
Marcus in
the 27th
chapter of
Acts did
that.
Paul was
a prisoner.
Paul had
been in
jail for
the gospel
for a
period of
time,
a long
period of
time.
He finally
appealed to
Caesar and
said,
to Caesar
you go,
and they
put him
on a
boat for
prisoners.
And when
you read
Acts 27,
it's really
clear that
they were
still
committing
this whole
idea that
one person
doesn't
go,
because Paul
figured I'm
going to
preach the
gospel to
the Caesar
going to
the court.
This isn't
a bad thing,
this is a
good thing.
You know,
Romans paid
for me to
get to
them.
But they
always went
as a
king,
always
as a
king.
And so
Luke gets
onto the
boat,
probably
signed
on as
a
doctor,
but then
it tells
us that
Aristarchus
got onto
the boat
as well,
and Luke
said the
only way
he could
have done
that was
by signing
up to be
Paul's
slave.
Paul is
a Roman
citizen,
and Roman
citizens
were
allowed to
take a
personal
slave,
so
committed
to the
gospel
of
Jesus
Christ
and to
this
team
ministry
together
that I'll
sign on
and hear the
livid,
hear the
message on
the boat.
Because the
Romans weren't
done.
12 days
of 100
year prayer,
12 months,
spent
the first
missionaries,
and ended
up going
to five
continents
in the
Caribbean.
By the
time,
Count
Vincendorf
was kind
of the
person
that God
used to
gel them
all
together.
By the
time
they
all
got
together,
in
Dork's
life,
one out
of 12
Moravians
ended up
as part
of the
missionary
team.
One out
of 12.
And I'm
not talking
about
the
Scripture
mission,
I mean
they
dedicated
their
life
to
the
missionaries.
One
of those
groups
considered
dedicated
to
going
across
the
Atlantic
and
the
boat
was in
this
incredible
storm.
John
Wesley
happened
to
be
on
the
boat.
John
Wesley
had
finished
books
that
I've
read
my
whole
life
in
a few
years.
And
everybody
was
panicking
because of
the
storm,
except
the
Moravians
who were
in one
corner,
they were
praying,
worshipping
God,
and then
they were
going out
comforting
all of
their
co-workers.
Wesley
was so
impressed
that he
went and
sought out
the
Moravians
and his
testimony
is that
it led
to his
autoscape
conversion.
He became
one of the
fathers of
the first
great
awakening.
The
Moravians
impacted
the first
great
awakening.
William
Currie,
who was
the father
of the
modern
missionary
movement,
said,
quote,
see what
the
Moravians
have
done.
Can
we
not
follow
their
example?
And
thanks to
God,
it's
the Lord.
What led
to this
unbelievable
movement?
I'll
try to
do this
quickly.
First of all,
a disclaimer,
God used
a bunch
of things.
But the
number one
thing he
used was,
quote,
an abiding,
commodified,
absolute
commitment to
one and
a whole.
A great
personal
sacrifice and
ungodly
humility and
boldness,
Zinsendorf,
who was the
Count,
came and
moved in
with some
raising
people and
convinced
them to
sign what
he called
the
brotherly
agreement
for
unity
and
accountability.
And then
for the
next decade,
lived that
commitment
out.
Someone said
that Zinsendorf
added fellowship
of the
third sacrament
Protestant
Church,
committed
to
committing
out one
another to
actually
doing the
one another
with each
other.
So much
further
became the
foundation of
the outpouring
of the
Holy Spirit.
just a few
hundred
believers
who literally
turned the
world upside
down.
Jesus said
that I
don't know you
and my
disciples by
your loved
ones or
mother.
I'm not
going to pull
up the
gallery
commitment
unless you
get nervous
in front of
me.
It's
humbling.
commitment
level
that they
did.
But I
only can
at least
a
miscommit
to one
another
in tangible
ways
according to
the words
of Jesus
so that
they will
know you
are my
disciples
by your
loved ones
and others.
As Ryan
comes in
an interesting
reunion of
the final
act,
consider this
as you
participate
in
communion.